Chapter 134.
The chase. Second day.
At daybreak, the three mast heads were punctually manned aresh. Do you see him?
cried Ahab, after allowing a little space for the light to spread.
See nothing, sir. Turn up all hands and make sail. He travels faster than I
thought for. The tag gallon sails. I They should have been kept on her all
night, but no matter, it is but resting for the rush. Here be it said that this
pertinent pursuit of one particular whale continued through day into night
and through night into day is a thing by no means unprecedented in the South Sea
fishery. For such is the wonderful skill, precience of experience, and
invincible confidence acquired by some great natural geniuses among the
Nantucket commanders, that from the simple observation of a whale, when last
described, they will, under certain given circumstances, pretty accurately
foretell both the direction in which he will continue to swim for a time while
out of sight, as well as his probable rate of progression during that period.
and in these cases somewhat as a pilot when about losing sight of the coast
whose general trending he well knows and which he desires shortly to return to
again but at some further point like as this pilot stands by his compass and
takes the precise bearing of the cape at present visible in order the more
certainly to hit a right the remote unseen headland eventually to be visited
so does the fisherman at his compass with the whale for after being chased
and diligently ly marked through several hours of daylight. Then, when night
obscures the fish, the creature's future wake through the darkness is almost as
established to the sagacious mind of the hunter as the pilot's coast is to him.
So that to this hunter's wondrous skill, the proverbial eancence of a thing writes
desired purposes well nigh as reliable as the steadfast land. And as the mighty
iron leviathan of the modern railway is so familiarly known in its every pace
that with watches in their hands, men time his rate as doctors that of a
baby's pulse, and lightly say of it, the uptrain or the downtrain will reach such
and such a spot at such and such an hour. Even so, almost there are
occasions when these Nantucketers time that other Leviathan of the deep,
according to the observed humor of his speed, and say to themselves, "So many
hours hence, this whale will have gone 200 m, will have about reached this, or
that degree of latitude or longitude.
But to render this acuteness at all successful in the end, the wind and the
sea must be the whaleman's allies. For of what present avail to the becomed or
windbound mariner is the skill that assures him that he is exactly 93
leagues and a quarter from his port.
Inferable from these statements are many collateral subtle matters touching the
chase of Wales. The ship tore on leaving such a furrow in the sea as when a
cannonball miss becomes a plowshare and turns up the level field.
by salt and hemp, cried Stub. But this swift motion of the deck creeps up one's
legs and tingles at the heart. This ship and I are two brave fellows. Haha.
Someone take me up and launch me spinewise on the sea. For by live oaks
my spine's a keel. Haha. We go the gate that leaves no dust behind.
There she blows. She blows. She blows right ahead. Was now the mast head cry.
I I cried Stub. I knew it. You can't escape. Blow on and split your spout
whale. The mad fiend himself is after you. Blow your trump. Blister your
lungs. Ahab will dam off your blood as a miller shuts his Watergate upon the stream.
And Stub did but speak out for well nigh all the crew. The frenzies of the chase
had by this time worked them bubblingly up, like old wine worked a new. Whatever
pale fears and forboding some of them might have felt before, these were not
only now kept out of sight through the growing awe of Ahab, but they were
broken up and on all sides routed as timid prairie hairs that scatter before
the bounding bison. The hand of fate had snatched all their souls, and by these
stirring perils of the previous day, the rack of the past night's suspense, the
fixed, unfearing, blind, reckless way in which their wild craft went plunging
toward its flying mark. By all these things their hearts were bowled along,
the wind that made great bellies of their sails, and rushed the vessel on by
arms, invisible as irresistible.
This seemed the symbol of that unseen agency which so enslaved them to the race.
They were one man, not 30. For as the one ship that held them all, though it
was put together of all contrasting things, oak and maple and pinewood, iron
and pitch and hemp, yet all these ran into each other into the one concrete
hull, which shot on its way, both balanced and directed by the long
central keel. Even so, all the individualities of the crew, this man's
valor, that man's fear, guilt, and guiltiness, all varieties were welded
into oneness, and were all directed to that fatal goal which Ahab, their one
lord and keel, did point to.
The rigging lived. The mast heads, like the tops of tall palms, were
outspreadingly tufted with arms and legs, clinging to a spar with one hand.
Some reached forth the other with impatient wavings. Others, shading their
eyes from the vivid sunlight, sat far out on the rocking yards. All the spars
in full bearing of mortals, ready and ripe for their fate. Ah, how they still
strove through that infinite bless to seek out the thing that might destroy
them. Why sing you not out for him if you see him? cried Ahab, when, after the
lapse of some minutes since the first cry, no more had been heard. Sway me up,
men. You have been deceived. Not Moby Dick cast one odd jet that way and then disappears.
It was even so. In their headlong eagerness, the men had mistaken some
other thing for the whale spout, as the event itself soon proved. For hardly had
Ahab reached his perch, hardly was the rope bellayed to its pin on the deck,
when he struck the keynote to an orchestra that made the air vibrate, as
with the combined discharges of rifles.
The triumphant hallow of 30 buckskin lungs was heard, as much nearer to the
ship than the place of the imaginary jet, Moby Dick bodily burst into view.
For not by any calm or indolent spoutings, not by the peaceable gush of
that mystic fountain in his head, did the white whale now reveal his vicinity,
but by the far more wondrous phenomenon of breaching, rising with his utmost
velocity from the furthest depths, the sperm whale thus booms his entire bulk
into the pure element of air, and piling up a mountain of dazzling foam, shows
his place to the distance of 7 mi or more. In those moments, the torn,
enraged waves he shakes off seem his man. In some cases, this breaching is his act of defiance.
There she breaches. There she breaches, was the cry, as in his immeasurable
bravados, the white whale tossed himself salmon-like to heaven, so suddenly seen
in the blue plain of the sea, and relieved against the still bluer margin
of the sky. The spray that he raised for the moment intolerably glittered and
glared like a glacier, and stood there gradually fading and fading away from
its first sparkling intensity to the dim mistiness of an advancing shower in a veil.
I breach your last to the sun, Moby Dick, cried Ahab. Thy hour and thy
harpoon are at hand. Down, down, all of you, but one man at the four. The boats
stand by.
Unmindful of the tedious rope ladders of the shrouds, the men, like shooting
stars slid to the deck by the isolated backstays and howiards, while Ahab, less
dartingly but still rapidly, was dropped from his perch. "Lower away!" he cried
so soon as he had reached his boat, a spare one rigged the afternoon previous.
"Mr. Starbucks, the ship is thine. Keep away from the boats, but keep near them.
Lower all."
As if to strike a quick terror into them, by this time being the first
asalent himself, Moby Dick had turned and was now coming for the three crews.
Ahab's boat was central, and cheering his men, he told them he would take the
whale head and head, that is, pull straight up to his forehead, a not
uncommon thing, for when within a certain limit such a course excludes the
coming onset from the whale's sidelong vision. But air that close limit was
gain, and while yet all three boats were plain as the ship's three mass to his
eye, the white whale, churning himself into furious speed, almost in an
instant, as it were, rushing among the boats with open jaws and a lashing tail,
offered appalling battle on every side, and heedless of the irons darted at him
from every boat, seemed only intent on annihilating each separate plank of
which those boats were made, but skillfully maneuvered Incessantly
wheeling like trained chargers in the field, the boats for a while eluded him,
though at times but by a plank's breadth, while all the time Ahab's
unearly slogan tore every other cry but his to shreds.
But at last, in his untraceable evolutions, the white whales so crossed
and recrossed, and in a thousand ways entangled these slack of the three lines
now fast to him, that they foreshortened, and of themselves warped
the devoted boats toward the planted irons in him, though now for a moment
the whale drew aside a little, as if to rally for a more tremendous charge.
Seizing that opportunity, Ahab first paid out more line, and then was rapidly
hauling and jerking in upon it again, hoping that way to disencumber it of
some snarls, when, lo, a sight more savage than the embattled teeth of
sharks, caught and twisted, corkscrewed in the mazes of the line, loose harpoons
and lances, with all their bristling barbs and points, came flashing and
dripping up to the chalks in the boughs of Ahab's boat. Only one thing could be
done. Seizing the boat knife, he critically reached within, through, and
then without the rays of steel, dragged in the line beyond, passed it inboard to
the bowsman, and then, twice sundering the rope near the chocks, dropped the
intercepted of steel into the sea, and was all fast again. That
instant the white whale made a sudden rush among the remaining tangles of the
other lines, by so doing irresistibly dragged the more involved boats of stub
and flask toward his flukes, dashed them together like two rolling husks on a
surfbeaten beach, and then diving down into the sea, disappeared in a boiling
malstrm, in which for a space the odorous cedar chips of the Rex danced
round and round like the grated nutmeg in a swiftly stirred bowl of punch.
punch.
While the two crews were yet circling in the waters, reaching out after the
revolving line tubs, ores, and other floating furniture, while a slope little
flask bobbed up and down like an empty vial, twitching his legs upwards to
escape the dreaded jaws of sharks, and Stub was lustily singing out for someone
to ladle him up. And while the old man's line, now parting, admitted of his
pulling into the creamy pool to rescue whom he could, in that wild
simultaneousness of a thousand concreted perils, Ahab's yet unstricken boat
seemed drawn up towards heaven by invisible wires, as arrowlike, shooting
perpendicularly from the sea, the white whale dashed his broad forehead against
its bottom, and sent it turning over and over into the air till it fell again,
gunnled downward. wards and Ahab and his men struggled from out under it like
seals from a seaside cave.
The first uprising momentum of the whale, modifying its direction as he
struck the surface, involuntarily launched him along it to a little
distance from the center of the destruction he had made, and with his
back to it he now lay for a moment slowly feeling with his flukes from side
to side. And whenever a stray ore bit of plank the least chip or crumb of the
boats touched his skin, his tail swiftly drew back and came sideways smiting the
sea. But soon, as if satisfied that his work for that time was done, he pushed
his pleated forehead through the ocean, and trailing after him the intertangled
lines, continued his lured way at a traveler's methodic pace.
As before, the attentive ship, having described the whole fight, again came
bearing down to the rescue, and dropping a boat, picked up the floating mariners,
tubs, orars, and whatever else could be caught at, and safely landed them on her
decks. Some sprained shoulders, wrists, ankles, livid contusions, wrenched
harpoons, and lances, inextricable intricacies of rope, shattered ores, and
planks. All these were there, but no fatal or even serious ill seemed to have
befallen anyone. As with Fidala the day before, so Ahab was now found grimly
clinging to his boat's broken half, which afforded a comparatively easy
float, nor did it so exhaust him as the previous day's mishap. But when he was
helped to the deck, all eyes were fastened upon him, as instead of
standing by himself, he still half hung upon the shoulder of Starbucks, who had
thus far been the foremost to assist him. His ivory leg had been snapped off,
leaving but one short, sharp splinter.
"I, I, Starbucks." It is sweet to lean sometimes, be the leaner who he will,
and would old Ahab had leaned often than he has.
The feral has not stood, sir, said the carpenter now coming up. I put good work
into that leg.
But no bones broken, sir, I hope, said Stub, with true concern. I And all
splintered to pieces, Stub. Do you see it? But even with a broken bone, old
Ahab is untouched. And I account no living bone of mine one jot more me than
this dead one that's lost. Nor white whale nor man nor fiend can so much as
graze old Ahab in his own proper and inaccessible being. Can any lead touch
yonder floor? Any mast scrape yonder roof? A loft there. Which way? Dead to
lured sir. Uphelm then. Pile on the sail again. Shipkeepers down the rest of the
spare boats and rig them. Mr. Starbucks, away and muster the boat's cruise. Let
me first help thee towards the bull work, sir. Oh. Oh. Oh, how this splinter
gores me now. A cursed fate that the unconquerable captain in the soul should
have such a craven mate. Sir, my body man, not thee. Give me something for a
cane. There, that shivered lance will do. Muster the men. Surely I have not
seen him yet. By heaven, it cannot be.
Missing. Quick, call them all.
The old man's hinted thought was true.
Upon mustering the company, the parsey was not there. The parsey? Cried Stub.
He must have been caught in the black vomit wrench thee. Run all of ye above
hello cabin folk, find him. Not gone.
Not gone. But quickly they returned to him with the tidings that the parsy was
nowhere to be found. I, sir, said Stub, caught among the tangles of your line. I
thought I saw him dragging under. My line. My line. Gone. Gone.
What means that little word? What death nail rings in it? That old Ahab shakes
as if he were the belfry. The harpoon too. Toss over the litter there. Do you
see it? The forged iron man. The white whales. No, no, no. Blististered fool.
This hand did dart it. It is in the fish. A loft there. Keep him nailed
quick. All hands to the rigging of the boats. Collect the oars. Harpooners, the
irons, the irons. Hoist the royals higher. I'll pull on all the sheets.
Helm there. Steady, steady for your life. I'll 10 times girdle the
unmeasured globe. Yay. And drive straight through it. But I'll slay him yet.
Great God. But for one single instant show thyself, cried Starbucks. Never,
never wil thou capture him, old man. In Jesus' name, no more of this. That's
worse than devil's madness. Two days chase, twice stove to splinters, thy
very leg once more snatched from under thee, thy evil shadow gone, all good
angels mobbing thee with warnings. What more thou have? Shall we keep chasing
this murderous fish till he swamps the last man? Shall we be dragged by him to
the bottom of the sea? Shall we be towed by him to the infernal world? Oh, oh,
impiiety and blasphemy to hunt him more, Starbucks. Of late I felt strangely
moved to thee. Ever since that hour we both saw, thou knowest what in each
other's eyes, but in this matter of the whale be the front of thy face to me as
the palm of this hand, a lipless, unfeatured blank. Ahab is forever Ahab
man. This whole acts immutably decreed.
It was rehearsed by thee and me a billion years before this ocean rolled.
Fool. I am the fate's lieutenant. I act under orders. Look thou underling that
thou obeyest mine. Stand round me men.
You see an old man cut down to the stump leaning on a shivered lance propped up
on a lonely foot. It is Ahab, his body's part. But Ahab's souls a centipede that
moves upon a hundred legs. I feel strained, half stranded as ropes that
tow dismastered frigots in a gale. And I may look so, but air I break, you'll
hear me crack. Until you hear that, know that Ahab's hauer toes his purpose yet.
Believe ye men in the things called omens. Then laugh aloud and cry encore
for air they drown. Drowning things will twice rise to the surface. Then rise
again to sink forever more. So with Moby Dick. Two days he's floated. Tomorrow
will be the third. I men. He'll rise once more but only to spout his last. Do
you feel brave men? Brave as fearless fire? Cried Stub.
and is mechanical," muttered Ahab. Then, as the men went forward, he muttered on
the things called omens. And yesterday I talked the same to Starbucks there
concerning my broken boat. Oh, how valiantly I seek to drive out of others
hearts what's clenched so fast in mine.
The Parsy, the Parsy gone, gone. and he was to go before, but still was to be
seen again. Air I could perish. How's that? There's a riddle now might baffle
all the lawyers backed by the ghosts of the whole line of judges. Like a hawk's
beak, it pecks my brain. I'll I'll solve it, though.
When dusk descended, the whale was still in sight to lure. So once more the sail
was shortened and everything passed nearly as on the previous night. Only
the sound of hammers and the hum of the grindstone was heard till nearly
daylight as the men toiled by lanterns in the complete and careful rigging of
the spare boats and sharpening their fresh weapons for the tomorrow.
Meanwhile, of the broken keel of Ahab's wrecked craft, the carpenter made him
another leg, while still, as on the night before, slouched Ahab stood fixed
within his scuttle, his hid helotrope glance anticipatingly gone backward on
its dial, sat due eastward for the earliest sun.